ACTWU's Office of Corporate and Financial Affairs Records 5619/025
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU's Office of Corporate and Financial Affairs Records
1976-1995
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Office of Corporate and Financial Affairs
5619/025
4 cubic feet
4 linear feet
Correspondence, reports, publications.
This collection consists of correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, and files from the Office of Corporate and Financial Affiars of the Amalgamated Clothing and Textiles Workers' Union. There is also a small amount of material from ACWA's Office of Corpoarate and Financila Affairs scattered throughout the collections
6791909
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
May 19, 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, July 2010
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America All other 5619 collections. And 6000/026: UNITE's Office of Corporate and Financial Affairs Records
Textile workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Office of Corporate and Financial Affairs --Archives; Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Office of Corporate and Financial Affairs --Archives; Barrett Resources Corporation --Archives; Dixie Yarns --Archives; Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. --Archives; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees; Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees. Office of Corporate and Financial Affairs --Archives; UNITE (Organization) --Archives; United States. Occupational Safety and Health Administration --Archives
6791909
- Cannon Retirees for Full Pensions, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Congressional Hearing on Insurance Company Failures, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Pension Plans
- Political Contributions to Terry Sanford, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- North Carolina Activity on Pension Plans, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Congressional Reports and Polls, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Wisconsin, International Union of Electronic, Electrical, Salaried, Machine and Furniture Workers, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- First Executive Corp., 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Newspaper Articles on Pension Plans, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Insurance Forum, Critique, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 10-K Report, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Senate Subcommittee on Labor, Retirement Issue, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Insurance Commissioner of the State of California, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- North Carolina Life and Accident and Health Insurance Guaranty Association, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Senator Terry Sanford Hearing, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Annuity Information, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc., 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- First Executive Fines, 1984-1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Insurance Company Records, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 8-K Report, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Terry Sanford, Political Contributions, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Cardiss Collins, Hearing, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- California Conservatorship Filings, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- The Insurance Forum Vol. 15, No. 10, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Sanford Hearing, Testimony, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- First Executive Corp. Legal Documents, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Press Release on Union Lies, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- FOIA Request and Response, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Department of Labor Complaint, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- FOIA Information, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Economic Benefits, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Stock Ownership, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Uniform Commercial Code Filings, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Insurance and Pension FOIAs, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Health and Safety Issues, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- US District Court of Northern California, Kayes v. Pacific Lumber Co., 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  EEOC, Americans with Disabilities Act
- First Annuity Corp. Proposal, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Shop Floor Literature, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Takeover Articles, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Articles, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Takeover, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- NLRB Complaint on Fieldcrest Cannon's Unfair Labor Practices, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Newspaper Articles on the Cannon Retirement Issue, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Cannon Retirement Program, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Notes on Meetings with Bob Giolito and Ian Lanoff (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Notes on Fieldcrest Documents, 1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- 5310 Termination Notice, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Economic Benefits, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- ACTWU v. David Murdock, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- UFCW and Sweet Sue Kitchens, Inc., 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- B&C Associates and Lee Apparel Co., 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- B&C Associates, Tultex, 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Robert Brown and South Africa, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- NLRB, Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc., 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- B&C Associates and Robert Brown, 1990-1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Rowan County Profile, 1988-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Review of Haynesworth File, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Airplane Information, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Fitzgibbons' Businesses, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Fitzgibbons' Union Connections, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Navy Ships and Cannon Mills Co., 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Army Contracts, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Government Contracts, Terms and Conditions, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Government Contracts with Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc., 1985-1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Navy Contracts, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Communication on Cannon Workers Pension Plans, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- B&C Associates, Ball and Chain pamphlet, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Concerned Citizens, Payments to Publishing Companies, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Cannon Mills, Plant Closing, 1982-1993 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Confidentiality Agreement, Amoskeag Co. and Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Confidential Preliminary Offering of Stock Shares, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Stock Shares, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- ACTWU Stock Ownership, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Union Bid, ESOP, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  Notes and Letters
- 401(k) Plan Design, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Legal Research on Fieldcrest Cannon and Amoskeag, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Stockholders Annual Meeting, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Collective Bargaining, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Stock Offering and Senior Debentures, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Law Suit, Rand v. Fieldcrest Cannon, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Coleman Co., Withdrawal of Annuity Plan, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Health and Safety Data, 1987-1995 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- US District Court of Southern New York, ACTWU v. Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Newspaper Articles, Court rules against Fieldcrest, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Newspaper Articles, First Executive Insurance Cuts and Fieldcrest Protests, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Newspaper Articles, Fieldcrest Cannon, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Newspaper Articles, Cannon Retirement Cuts, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Anti-Union and Pro-Union Campaigns, Fieldcrest, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Employee, Retirement Plan Documents, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Court Hearings, Recorded Testimonies, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Communications on Pensions, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- ACTWU Law Suit Settlement Distribution, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Murdock Lawsuit, Fieldcrest Filings, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Murdock Lawsuit, Settlement Documents, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Murdock Lawsuit Complaint, 1985-1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Settlement Distribution List, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Murdock Lawsuit, Plaintiff's Request for Production of Documents, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Strike Threat, Newspaper Articles, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Pension Problem, Miscellaneous Documents, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Letters Regarding Cannon Holding Corporation and the SEC Filing, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Interrogatories, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Deposition of R. Derwood Bost, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Answer of Defendants and Plaintiff's Memorandum, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Deposition of Murdock, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Request for Production Documents and Deposition of Messmer, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Deposition of Messmer and Other Documents, 1979-1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Keystone Pension and Newspaper Articles, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Deposition of Brandon Jones and Trustee Documents, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- ACTWU v. Murdock, Kaiser Cement, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Strike, Press, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Newspaper Articles on Murdock, 1980-1991 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Fieldcrest Mills, Press Before Cannon, 1982-1988 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Murdock, Press, 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Newspaper Articles on ACTWU Organizing Campaign, K-Town, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Organizing, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- ACTWU v. Fieldcrest Cannon, Inc. Lawsuit Complaint, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Battle over Trusts, Preparation Notes, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Fieldcrest Cannon under the Securities Exchange Act, Form S-3, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Cannon Pension Payments, Press Articles and Documents, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Future Cannon Suit, Sigman and Lewis, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Reference Documents on Pensions, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Health and Safety, Asbestos, 1989-1997 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Health and Safety, Asbestos in Columbus, GA, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Health and Safety, North Carolina Plant, Employee Background, 1989-1996 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Health and Safety, Asbestos in Union Plants, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Asbestos, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  OSHA regulations and fines
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Worker Background, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Cannon Asbestos Survey, 1982-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Cannon, Compressed Air Violations, 1977-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Health and Safety, Paul Gundlach, 1986-1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Virginia Workers' Compensation, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Asbestos Reports, North Carolina Department of Environment, Health and Natural Resources, 1990-1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- North Carolina, OSHA Printout, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- OSHA Citations, 1976-1995 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Plant 1
- OSHA Citations, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Plant 4
- OSHA Citations, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Plant 6
- OSHA Citations, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Plant 5
- OSHA Citations, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Plant 9
- OSHA Citations, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Plant 10
- OSHA Citations, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Plant 11
- OSHA Citations, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Plant 15
- Asbestos, Health Background Information (Box 4, Folder 15)
- OSHA Citations, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Plant 17
- OSHA Citations, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  East Stadium Dr.
- OSHA Citations, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  Draper Sheet
- OSHA Citations, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Plant 14
- OSHA Citations, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Karastan
- OSHA Citations, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Greigg Mill
- OSHA Citations, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Alexander Sheeting
- OSHA Citations, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  Greenville, NC
- OSHA Citations, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  Smithfield Auto-Blanket
- OSHA Citations, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Riverside Dr
- OSHA, Department of Labor Printout, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Alabama
- OSHA, Department of Labor Printout, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Georgia
- OSHA, Department of Labor Printout, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Virginia
- First Piedmont Report on Fieldcrest Cannon, Removal of Ceiling Tiles, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Fieldcrest Cannon Health and Safety, Photographs (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Summaries of Asbestos, 1988-1995 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Status and Location
- Fieldcrest Cannon Asbestos, Memos and Incidents, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Exposure to Cotton Dust and Swink Sheet, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Dumping References, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Asbestos Monitoring Reports, 1987-1994 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Maps of Plants and Facilities (Box 4, Folder 36)
- S&ME, Inc. Report, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Plant 7 Surveys, 1982-1993 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Plant 1 Surveys, 1982-1988 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Swink Sheet Surveys, 1982-1991 (Box 4, Folder 40)
- S&ME, Asbestos Survey on Mill #5, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- United Paperworkers International Union and James River Corp., 1989-1996 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Fieldcrest Cannon, Union Flyers, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Bangor & Arostoock, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Podesta Associates, Inc., 1994 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Walmart Court Decisions and Newspaper Articles, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Walmart, Original Articles on Proxy Votes, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Walmart Settlement Decisions, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Walmart, Proxy and SEC Notes, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Walmart, EEO Lawsuit, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 50)
- Walmart, EEO Research, 1981-1992 (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Walmart, Lawsuit, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  ACTWU, Jennifer Florin
- ACTWU v. Walmart, Lawsuit, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Walmart, SEC Form 10-K Annual Reports, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 54)
- Walmart Annual Meeting, Lichtenberg, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 55)
- Walmart, Annual Meeting Reports and Documents, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 56)
- Walmart Litigation Documents, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Walmart, SEC Form 10-Q and Form 10-K Annual Reports, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 58)
- ACTWU, ILGWU and Zensen, 6th Joint Conference, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  Honolulu, HI